hey everyone welcome back to this Tosca
playlist and today we are going to talk
about another authentication type which
is digest authentication now this
authentication mechanism may be used
with some API messages or requests and
you need to make sure that you are using
uh the correct authentication type for
your API message before you send them
right
now in the previous session we already
looked at how you can use the basic
authentication using a simple username
and password so if you have not watched
the video URL is on the top so go ahead
and watch that before you start watching
this particular video which is the next
authentication type which is digest
Authentication
okay
so before we get into digest
Authentication
uh let's first understand what's the
difference between basic authentication
and digest authentication because on the
front end when I use this particular API
message you will not see any difference
which I mean is I'll be sending this
request with another username and
password but as I said there will be no
difference because in basic auth also we
send an username and password
and in the digest art also we are
sending a username and password
but the difference is digest
authentication is much more uh you can
say Advanced authentication type okay
rather than just sending the username
and password internally a lot of other
things happen Okay so let's try and
understand this little better with this
particular diagram okay and here you can
see that there are multiple requests and
responses which are coming and going
back instead of just one request and
response in the case of basic
authentication right where you send a
get request with a particular username
and password and the server uh
authorizes that request and sends back
the response okay but that's not the
case with Digest auth
so in this particular authentication
mechanism right what happens is when we
send a particular get request from any
HTTP client right like our Tosca in this
case
okay so the server will respond back
with a 401 unauthorized okay but uh even
if it is four zero one unauthorized in
the header we get some authentication
information okay so which is the www
authenticate okay this will be the
header name and then inside this you
will find uh two values which is
um a realm and nonce values which will
be used uh to Hash the subsequent
requests okay
so a hashing mechanism is applied to
protect uh the particular request which
is being sent to the server and which
will be authenticated using a particular
username and password and so in the next
request uh which will be sent by the
client
it will include this authorization
header with the information which was
sent by the server which was this ww
authenticate header Okay so so when we
send this highest information from the
client to the server then the server can
authorize this particular request and it
will send back a 200 okay response with
the particular response payload okay so
instead of just 2 or request and
response there are four okay so there
are two requests and two responses
coming back from the server okay and
that's the difference between basic
authentication and digest Authentication
but as I said you will not see any
difference in the front end on the HTTP
client side because internally Tosca is
able to do all of this for you okay
so now let's go back and let's try to
use uh or create another API message
where we can use this digest
authentication right
so I'm going to create a new message
here and I'm going to call it Digest
okay and here again in the end point
I'm going to use a particular endpoint
right
and for this I'm going to use
um
API which is available with Tosca okay
one of the sample apis which is the
secured employee version 2.
okay and this is protected by digest
authentication right so it's
webservice.cloud.com rest API secure
employee version 2. okay
now if I just send this particular
request without any authentication
obviously we are going to get 401 on
authorized right
but uh if I go back to my request and I
now select uh digest Authentication
and for this I'm going to pass the
username and password
okay
and then I'm going to send this
particular request
okay and this time around you will see
that we got a status code 200 okay okay
with the particular payload which is the
employee information
okay but as I said internally Tosca is
sending two requests but you cannot see
that in here okay so that's how you use
the digest authentication for any
particular API requests which are
protected by this particular mechanism
okay
so this was all for this particular
video where we looked at the digest
authentication type okay there are many
other authentication types which we may
look in our other sessions but hopefully
this was helpful for you and helped you
learning something new
so do tune in to our channel uh to watch
more interesting videos on API testing
um with Tosca and we'll also keep adding
more videos on other topics if you have
any Topic in your mind then do share it
in the comment section and will pick up
that particular topic for learning Tosca
also if you have not subscribed please
do subscribe so that you get a
notification whenever a new video is
added uh deleted and this will help you
to keep learning Tosca in a continuous
manner
so thank you for watching and until the
next video keep watching and keep
learning Tosca